<?xml version="1.0" standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE manpage SYSTEM "http://masqmail.cx/xmltoman/xmltoman.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://masqmail.cx/xmltoman/xmltoman.xsl" ?>
<!-- $Id: saslfinger.1.xml 21 2005-01-10 23:10:54Z p $ -->

<manpage name="saslfinger" section="1" desc="A utility to collect SMTP AUTH relevant configuration for Postfix">

<synopsis>
<cmd>saslfinger [-chs]</cmd>
</synopsis>

<description>
	<p>saslfinger is a utility to collect SMTP AUTH relevant configuration
	for Postfix. Depending on how you run it, it will search for information
	on server-side or client-side SMTP AUTH configuration settings in
	Postfix and Cyrus SASL.</p>
</description>

<options>
<option>
	<p><opt>-c</opt></p>
<optdesc>
	<p>If you run saslfinger with the option <opt>-c</opt> it will collect
	data required for client-side SMTP AUTH. Client-side SMTP AUTH is when
	Postfix smtp daemon uses SMTP AUTH to authenticate itself with a remote
	mail server that offers SMTP AUTH.</p>

	<p>saslfinger will try to telnet to all hosts listed in
	smtp_sasl_password_maps, if it may read smtp_sasl_password_maps</p>

	<p>The telnet test verifies your host is able to reach the remote
	servers and shows what AUTH mechanisms they offer - in some cases this
	is required to debug client-side SMTP AUTH.</p>

	<p>Important: By default smtp_sasl_password_maps must be read-only to
	root, since these maps contain the usernames and passwords to
	authenticate. If you run saslfinger as root access will be no problem,
	but saslfinger will fail if you lack the permissions to access
	smtp_sasl_password_maps.</p>

	<p>If you want to run the telnet test, but don't want to run saslfinger
	as root change permissions of smtp_sasl_password_maps so that the user
	running saslfinger may access <b>smtp_sasl_password_maps</b> while you
	debug.</p>

	<p>*note: You don't need to worry about saslfinger doing anything with
	the username or password stored next to the remote hosts in your
	<b>smtp_sasl_password_maps</b>; saslfinger completely ignores these
	informations!</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
	<p><opt>-h</opt></p>
<optdesc>
	<p>If you run saslfinger with the option <opt>-h</opt> it will print a
	little help message that tells you about the options you can use.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
	<p><opt>-s</opt></p>
<optdesc>
	<p>If you run saslfinger with the option <opt>-s</opt> it will collect
	data required for server-side SMTP AUTH. Server-side SMTP AUTH is when
	Postfix smtpd daemon offers SMTP AUTH to mail clients.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

</options>

<section name = "Files">
<p><file>saslfinger</file> - the script you need to run.</p>
<p><file>saslfinger.1</file> - the man page you are currently reading.</p>
</section>

<section name = "Author">
	<p>Patrick Koetter, &lt;patrick.koetter@state-of-mind.de&gt;, <url
	href="http://www.state-of-mind.de"/></p>

	<p>You will find the newest version of saslfinger at <url
	href="http://postfix.state-of-mind.de/patrick.koetter/saslfinger/"/>.</p>
</section>

<section name = "Bugs">
	<p>Please report bugs to &lt;patrick.koetter@state-of-mind.de&gt;</p>
</section>
<!--
<section name = "See also">
<p>
<manref name="masqmail.conf" section="5" href="masqmail.conf.5.html"/>, <manref name="masqmail.route" section="5" href="masqmail.route.5.html"/>, <manref name="masqmail.get" section="5" href="masqmail.get.5.html"/>, <manref name="masqmail.aliases" section="5" href="masqmail.aliases.5.html"/>
</p>
</section>
-->
</manpage>
